Samuel George Morton Papers 1819-1850 Mss.B.M843
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 2.25 Linear feet 5 boxes, 486 items.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 4, 1837; 8" x 10"; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    New Haven, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (Page 3 contains letter from E.C. Herrick, to Dr. Morton, Feb. 3, 1837) Is including requested information from Herrick.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 5, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Cooper, William
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning collections of skulls in the city. Freeman Guide 3164.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 6, 1837; 7 1/2" x 12 3/4"; Troost, Gerard, 1776-1850
    Nashville, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning descriptions and skulls of Western Indians. Freeman Guide 1308.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 9, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning publication, fossils. Refers to a skull. Freeman Guide 1302.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 17, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
    Charleston, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning a new kind of hare. Refers to publications, Drs. Silliman, Cooper, Harlan, and Audubon.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 18, 1837; 8" x 10"; Piddington, Henry, 1797-1858
    [Calcutta] A.L.S. 2p. and add. Sending skulls.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Feb. 22, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 340.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l George Morton, March 4, 1837; 8" x 10"; Pitcher, Zina, 1797-1872
    Detroit, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Will send several skulls. Freeman Guide 2548.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 4, 1837; 7 1/2" x 12 3/4"; Troost, Gerard, 1776-1850
    Nashville University, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning drawings of skulls, position of Indians in the graves. Freeman Guide 1309.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 15, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
    Charleston, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning the hare.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 16, 1837; 8" x 8 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 16, 1837; 8 1/2" x 10 3/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 17, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
    Charleston, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning crania of Indians. Refers to Audubon and Dr. Harlan.Freeman Guide 3235.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, March 20, 1837; 7 1/2" x 9"; Dickson, Samuel Henry, 1798-1872
    Charleston, S.C., A.L.S. 1p. and add. Thanks for packet, including book.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 24, 1837; 7 1/2" x 11 1/2"; Troost, Gerard, 1776-1850
    Nashville, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Send drawings of heads. Refers to idols he collected. Freeman Guide 704.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 29, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sending letters from Maclure.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, March 30, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
    Charleston, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning a mistake in his manuscript.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 30, 1837; 7 1/4" x 9"; Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1790-1852
    Brighton, A.L.S. 4p. Fossils. Is sending geological specimens. Comments on a newspaper story about certain species surviving in acrid fluids.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, April 6, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April 7, 1837; 8" x 10"; Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856
    Boston, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 1519.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, April 16, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Maclure's views of proposed building.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, April 22, 1837; 8" x 10 1/4"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Maclure. Is sending box with specimens, including birds and animal skulls. Freeman Guide 2212.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, April 24, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
    Charleston, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Lepus. Mentions Pickering and Nuttall.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, April, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Holbrook, John Edwards, 1794-1871
    A.L.S. 1p. (Written on back of sheet addressed to Charles Pickering). Concerning skeleton of a "Peruvian." Freeman Guide 3696.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], May 2, 1837; 8 3/4" x 10 1/4"; Wied, Maximilian, Prinz von, 1782-1867
    Neuwied, A.L.S. 2p. Refers to his visit to Berlin. Concerning Morton's upcoming book on "American man," and skulls. Freeman Guide 468.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 9, 1837; 8 1/2" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 23, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning boxes with specimens he sent to various people.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, May 27, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Couthouy, Joseph Pitty, 1808-1864
    Boston, A.L.S. 4p.add. Concerning crania, Peruvian mummies. Refers to Mr. Blake. Freeman Guide 3165.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 3, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, June 12, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    Charleston, S.C., A.L.S. 1p. and add. Returned from expedition. In need of funds, requests money due from Academy.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 17, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, June 20, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Introduces William Hawkins.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, June 20, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 4p. Requested leave of absence from Dep. of State. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 29, 1837; 8" x 10"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Regarding Geological Survey of Ohio. Wants to procure certain books.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 29, 1837; 8" x 8"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
    Mexico, A.L.S. 1p. and add.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, July 3, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, July 8, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to M. Burrough, July 11, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
    Mexico, L. 2p. "Extract" (Probably in hand of M. Burrough). Concerning plan to pull down the Academy's old hall.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, July 13, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Is forwarding letters from Maclure. Plans to see Maclure before return to United States.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, July 13, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Evans, Edmund C.
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning crania. Freeman Guide 1507.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, July 16, 1837; 8" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Refers to Morton's wishes for skulls. Mentions a young artist. Is departing for England. Freeman Guide 1493.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, July 21, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Arrott, Colin (?)
    Paris, A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, July 21, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Maclure, and Burrough's intended "interview" with him.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, July 25, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
    A.L.S. 2p. add.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 4, 1837; 8" 1/4 x 8 1/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 5, 1837; 7 1/4" x 9"; Wood, S.
    London, A.L.S. 4p.add. Concerning minerals and skulls. Mentions Lord Kingsborough, and Lord and Lady Kingston. Freeman Guide 3170.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 7, 1837; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Ravenel, Edmund, 1797-1871
    Charleston, S.C., A.L.S. 4p.add. Unable to get crania, more likely to get fossils. Concerning shells. Includes drawing.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 10, 1837; 7 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, O., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning books for the Geological Survey of Ohio.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Aug. 10, 1837; 4 3/4" x 7 1/4"; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    Jardin de Roi, A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 14, 1837; 7" x 9"; Say, Lucy Way Sistaire, 1801-1886
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sends fossils for the Academy.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 28, 1837; 8" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    London, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Sending [plates of?] Birds of America to Wetherill, Academy and APS. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 28, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Sept. 26, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Sept. 29, 1837; 7 3/4" x 12 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning Maclure's will.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 1, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 8p. add. Concerning his visit to Maclure in Mexico.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Oct. 16, 1837; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning publications, fossils and shells. Is inquiring for "ancient heads."
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 20, 1837; 8" x 10"; Cramer, Charles
    St. Petersburg, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sending minerals for Academy, hoping for returns to Imperial Mineralogical Society.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 23, Oct. 24, 1837; 8 1/2" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning Maclure.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Nov. 2, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/4"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Nov. 7, 1837; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Friendly letter. Concerning Maclure. Refers to Hudson Foster.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Nov. 21, 1837; 8" x 10"; Houghton, Douglass, 1809-1845
    Detroit, L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Mentions Dr. Pitcher. Freeman Guide 2504.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 26, 1837; 8" x 12 1/2"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    London, A.L.S. 4p. add. "Duplicate" Concerning the return of Dr. Townshend from the Pacific. Ornithological news.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Dec. 26, 1837; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Dec. 26, 1837; 7 3/4" x 10"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning various boxes he sent. Mentions Townshend and Bachman.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 9, 1838; 5" x 8"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Townshend's birds. Mentions Exploring Expedition, and new edition of Michaux's work.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 17, 1838; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Has been sick. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 19, 1838; 8" x 9 3/4"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    London, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Mentions Ed. Harris and Dr. Sharpless. Ornithology.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 24, 1838; 8" x 10"; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning new edition of Michaux's Sylva. Mentions Maclure.
  - Letter to S[amuel] George Morton, Jan. 25, 1838; 7 3/4" x 12 3/4"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning the planned Expedition, and the new edition of Michaux.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Feb. 3, 1838; 8" x 10"; Abadie, E. H.
    Camp 3 miles from Lake Okee Chobee, A.L.S. 5p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls, Indian burials, disease among Indians. Freeman Guide 3233.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Feb. 6, 1838; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Geological specimens. Refers to Maclure.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 1, 1838; 8 1/2" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, March 3, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Hildreth, Samuel P. (Samuel Prescott), 1783-1863
    Marietta, O., A.L.S.1p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Also animal skulls. Freeman Guide 1303.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, March 13, 1838; 8" x 9 1/2"; Harris, Thaddeus William, 1795-1856
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 4p. add. Concerning Townshend's plan to reclaim and sell the insects collected by him.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 22, 1838; 7 1/4" x 9"; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    New Haven, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Thanks for Taylor's memoir, craniological drawings. Concerning sale of Mr. Mantell's museum.
  - Letter to S[amuel George] Morton, March 27, 1838; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Nasymth, Alexander, 1758-1840
    London, A.L.S. 4p.add. Concerning fossils.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 31, 1838; 8" x 10 1/2"; Burrough, Marmaduke
    Vera Crus, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Political conditions in Mexico. Mentions Maclure.
  - Letter to [Samuel] George Morton, April 2, 1838; 8" x 10"; Vargas, José María, 1786-1854
    Caracas, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 3169.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, April 4, 1838; 4 3/4" x 7 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning skulls. Freeman Guide 1497.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, April 6, 1838; 8" x 10"; Riddell, John Leonard, 1807-1867
    New Orleans, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Thanks for the books. Wants to subscribe to the Academy's Journal. Concerning reptiles.
  - Letter to [Samuel George Morton], April 19, 1838; 7" x 8 3/4"; Wied, Maximilian, Prinz von, 1782-1867
    Neuwied, A.L.S. 2p. Sending fossils. Concerning geological specimens, including minerals.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, April 29, 1838; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 5, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864
    Michilimackinac, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Indian annuities. Advice on where Morton can see Indians. Freeman Guide 2513.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 13, 1838; 8" x 9 1/2"; Anthony, John Gould, 1804-1877
    Cincinnati, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Geological fossils. Freeman Guide 2376.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, May 16, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Martin, J.
    Fort Cass, Calhoun, E. T[enn.], A(?) L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Cave near Fort Cass. Freeman Guide 689.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 31, 1838; 8" x 10"; Edmonds, Frederic
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Sending Indian skulls and minerals. Freeman Guide 2213.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, June 1, [1838]; 7 1/4" x 9"; Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1790-1852
    Clapham Common, near London, England, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concening his move from Brighton and planned sale of his collection. Geology.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 3, 1838; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, June 7, 1838; 7 3/4" x 10"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning whereabouts of John Shemo, who "deserted [a vessel]…and was now probably in Wilmington"
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, June 24, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Gibbons, William P. (William Peters), b. 1812
    Glenwood, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Sending specimans of Cicada.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 25, 1838; 8" x 10"; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
    Edinburgh, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning ornithology, business matters. Refers to skulls. Freeman Guide 1494.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, July 7, 1838; 7 1/4" x 9"; Audubon, Victor Gifford, 1809-1860
    London, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning "Birds of America." Refers to prints of crania.
  - Letter to S[amuel] George Morton, July 16, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Pickering, Charles, 1805-1878
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning whereabouts of John Shemo. Refers to Captain Wilkes' Expedition.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, July 28, 1838; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 1, 1838; 8" x 10"; Martin, J.
    Fort Cass, Calhoun, E. Tennessee, A(?)L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning crania. Cherokee. Freeman Guide 690.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 4, 1838; 8" x 10"; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Chicquesalunga near Manitta, Pa., A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning his desciption of a species of fish.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Aug. 6, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Powell, W. Byrd (William Byrd), 1799-1866
    Tuscumbia, Ala., A.L.S. 4p. add. Concerning his collection of crania. Freeman Guide 1305.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, Aug. 24, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 1/2"; Abadie, E. H.
    Picolata, E. Fla., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 3234.
  - Letter to Sam[uel] Geo[rge] Morton, Sept. 6, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Townsend, John Kirk, 1809-1851
    New Garden, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning Michener and his cabinet. Refers to fossils.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 16, 1838; 7 1/4" x 9"; Wood, S.
    Canterbury, A.L.S. 4p.add. Concerning animal skulls. Religious matters.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Oct. 19, 1838; 9 1/2" x 11 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p. and add. (On the reverse of this letter is a prospectus of a course of sixteen lectures on phrenology to be delivered by George Combe in Boston, October and November [1838]). Plans to inspect collection of American crania. Wants to offer class in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, Oct. 20, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864
    New Haven, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Concerning Mr. Dunn's notice for his journal.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Oct. 23, 1838; 8" x 10"; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. add. Concerning purchase of Morton's collection of shells, and his upcoming trip to Europe.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Oct. 28, 1838; 8" x 9 3/4"; Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Obliged for engravings.
  - Letter to [A.D. Bache], Oct. 28, [1838]; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Boston, Extract of L. 1p. (Transcribed by Dr. Bache in letter to S.G. Morton, Nov. 2, 1838.). Concerning phrenology.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Nov. 2, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. (Transcribes extract of letter from Geo. Combe, Oct. 28 [1838]). Concerning phrenology.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Dec. 3, 1838; 7 3/4" x 9 1/2"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning his election to the Academy.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Dec. 3, 1838; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Dec. 6, 1838; 7 1/2" x 12 3/4"; Troost, Gerard, 1776-1850
    Nashville, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning crania. Refers to articles fround in Indian graves. Freeman Guide 1310.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Dec. 25, 1838; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Dec. 28, 1838; 7 1/4" x 9"; Rodgers, J. Kearny (John Kearny), 1793-1851
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning a skull from Peru. Freeman Guide 3168.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, Jan. 1, 1839; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, Jan. 12, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858
    Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning new edition of Turner's work.
  - Letter to [Samuel George] Morton, Jan. 25, [1839?]; 4 3/4" x 7 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    [Philadelphia] A.L.S. 1p. and add. His collection is now available to copy in plaster.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, February 19, 1839; 7 3/4" x 10"; Dunn, Nathan
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Recommends John Notman as architect for new building of Academy.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 7, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858
    Brunswick, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 2948.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, March 11, 1839; 8" x 10"; Breck, Samuel, 1771-1862
    [Philadelphia] A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning geology.
  - Letter to Samuel G[eorge] Morton, March 19, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 1/2"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning phrenology.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l Geo[rge] Morton, March 31, 1839; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Gliddon, George R. (George Robins), 1809-1857
    Cairo, A.L.S. 8p. add. On difficulties of working in Egypt. Concerning skulls. Cost of shipping 93 skulls to Philadelphia.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, April 2, 1839; 8" x 10"; Harris, Thaddeus William, 1795-1856
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Wants to withdraw his description of Townshend's insects. Refers to Thomas Say's insect collection.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, April 10, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 1/4"; Clemens, James W.
    Wheeling, Va., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 1203.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, April 14, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning Indian skulls. Freeman Guide 1498.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 2, 1839; 7 3/4" x9 3/4"; Combe, George, 1788-1858
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning skulls. Discusses attendance at his lectures.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 2, 1839; 8" x 10"; Parker, Daniel &
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Introdes Mr. Ellis.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 8, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 1/4"; Clemens, James W.
    Wheeling, Va., A.L.S. 2p. and add. Introduces Jonas Crumbacher. Refers to skulls. Freeman Guide 1204.
  - Letter...to Dr. Hodgkin, May 20, 1839; 7" x 9"; Prichard, James Cowles, 1786-1848
    Bristol, Printed D. 2p. (On same sheet with letter from Thomas Hodgkin to S.G. Morton, Dec. 11,1839.) Letter in defense of the rights of native peoples.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, May 21, 1839; 7 1/2" x 9 1/4"; Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1790-1852
    Clapham Common, Surrey, England, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning geology, his book.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, May 23, 1839; 7 3/4" x 9 1/4"; Clemens, James W.
    Wheeling, Va., A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning beads found in a grave. Discusses skeletons of mastodons. Freeman Guide 1205.
  - Letter to Samuel George Morton, June 15, 1839; 8 1/4" x 10 1/2"; Maclure, William, 1763-1840
    Mexico, A.L.S. 2p. add. Signature reproduced in APS Proceedings, v.91,no.3,page 240.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, June 18, 1839; 7 1/4" x 8 3/4"; Nasymth, Alexander, 1758-1840
    London, A.L.S. 4p.add. Refers to an article he wrote. Requests gold.
  - Letter to Sam[ue]l G[eorge] Morton, July 19, 1839; 4 3/4" x 7 1/2"; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Plans to visit. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to S[amuel] G[eorge] Morton, July 29, 1839; 7 1/4" x 9"; Wood, S.
    Liverpool, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Concerning his work, travel plans. Refers to Morton's book on crania. Friendly letter.